Register of the Poland. Konsulat Generalny (New York, N.Y.) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Poland. Konsulat Generalny (New York, N.Y.) records,
1940-1948
76004
Poland. Konsulat Generalny (New York, N.Y.)
7 manuscript boxes (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, reports, agreements, minutes, histories, financial records, lists, press summaries, photographs, and printed matter, relating to the German and Soviet occupation of Poland during World War II, activities of the Polish Government-in-Exile (London), and displaced Polish citizens after World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Polish Consulate General in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Polish Consulate General in New York (Konsulat Generalny Rzeczpospolitej w Nowym Jorku) were obtained by the Hoover Institution in 1976 from the family of Consul General Sylwin Strakacz, three years after his death.
The New York Consulate was the first Polish diplomatic post on American soil after Poland regained its independence. It opened on August 1, 1918, much before the Polish Embassy in Washington and shortly before the San Francisco Consulate did (the latter remained open only for a short time, to facilitate the transfer of Poles remaining in Siberia). The New York office played a significant role, but these records deal mostly with civic and administrative affairs, not political ones.
What could be of particular interest to researchers are the efforts of the Polish diplomats in organizing relief among Polish Americans for their compatriots released from the Siberian camps in 1941, as well as the assistance to Polish prisoners of war in Germany throughout the war. From the same period, one will also find interesting documents on Polish-Soviet relations and on Polish-Jewish cooperation in the United States.
The collection is a good illustration of confusion among Polish diplomats in 1944-1945, caused by uncertainty about the future of their homeland and, subsequently, by the loss of recognition internationally (see the correspondence of Sylwin Strakacz with Tadeusz Gwiazdowski and Jan Ciechanowski, the Polish ambassador). One of the first posts of Poland's diplomatic network, the New York Consulate was also one of the first to fall, in 1945, to the communist takeover.
Some materials in the collection date from beyond the consulate's closing year. Since they related to the subject of Polish post-war politics, they were added to the consular records by Mr. Strakacz, who stayed in the United States after 1945 and remained active in émigré circles.
It is difficult to determine if the New York Consulate used the uniform system of classification recommended by the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Very likely, the order in which the documents came to the Hoover Institution was established by Mr. Strakacz himself.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Poles--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Poland.; United States--Foreign relations.; Poles--Soviet Union.
Series Description
- Office Files, 1941-1945. (Box 1)
  Budget records, receipts, and reports related to personnel affairs, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Correspondence, 1941-1949. (Box 1-2)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Sylwin Strakacz's correspondence is included here as well under his name, even though he was the consul general for some of the years listed
- Reports, 1943-1946. (Box 2-3)
  Reports issued by Polish government agencies on Poland's economy and foreign policy, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Subject File, 1941-1948. (Box 3-5)
  Fliers, clippings, brochures, newsletters, programs, reports, resolutions, maps, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Bulletins, 1946-1964. (Box 6)
  Bulletins issued by Polish Government-in-exil émigrés in London, Polish émigrés in the United States, and the British and American embassies in Warsaw, arranged alphabetically by alphabetically by title. These bulletins did not originate with the consulate, but were added later to the records by Sylwin Strakacz
- Printed Matter, 1942-1949. (Box 7)
  Brochures, programs, and periodicals, arranged alphabetically by title
Container List
- OFFICE FILES, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - General
    - General, 1941
      - May (Folder 1: 1)
      - September (Folder 1: 2)
  - Budget
    - 1944 - Receipts (Folder 1: 3)
    - 1945
      - General (Folder 1: 4)
      - Receipts (Folder 1: 5)
  - Closing operations, 1945-1946
    - General (Folder 1: 6)
    - Ciechanowski, Jan (Folder 1: 7)
  - Disciplinary Commission, 1942 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Employees - Personal characteristics, 1945 (Folder 1: 9)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1941-1949
  - General
    - General
      - 1941 (Folder 1: 10)
      - 1942 (Folder 1: 11)
      - 1946 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Prisoners of war
      - 1941 (Folder 1: 13)
      - 1942 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Arciszewski, Tomasz, 1945-1946 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Borkowski, E., Captain, 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Ciechanowski, Jan
    - 1942-1944 (Folder 1: 17)
    - 1945 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Felerski, Adam, 1943 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Figas, Justyn, 1942 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Gwiazdowski
    - 1945-1947 (Folder 1: 21)
    - 1949 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Interim Treasury Committee for Polish Questions, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Jachimowicz, A., 1942 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Kosciuszko Foundation, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Koszarski, Kazimierz, 1942 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Majewski, Kazimierz, 1942 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Marczynski, Dr., 1943 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw, 1947 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Paderewski, Ignacy, 1941 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Piskorski, Florian. (Folder 2: 9)
    Includes correspondence with Alex Habermann re transfer of funds from Swiss account, 1942
  - Poland. Ministerstwo Skarbu (Ministry of Finance), 1941-1945 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Polish Women's Alliance of America, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Pragier, Adam, 1945 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Ripa, Karol, 1943 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Sopicki, Stan, 1945 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Strakacz, Sylwin
    - 1940 (Folder 2: 15)
    - 1941 (Folder 2: 16)
    - 1942 (Folder 2: 17)
    - 1943 (Folder 2: 18)
    - 1944 (Folder 2: 19)
    - 1945 (Folder 2: 20)
    - 1946 (Folder 2: 21)
    - 1947 (Folder 2: 22)
    - 1957 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Swietlik, F. X., 1941-1943 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Szymczak, M. S., 1942 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Tarnowski, Adam, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Thackrey, T. O., 1945 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Tysowski, G., 1942 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Zygielbojm, Szmul, 1942 (Folder 2: 29)
- REPORTS, 1943-1946
  - Poland
    - Air transportation, Post-war, 1943 (Folder 2: 30)
    - Cultural losses in World War II, 1944 (Folder 2: 31)
    - Political conditions, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 32)
  - Polish Americans - Coordinating Committee of Polish American Associations in the East, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 33)
  - Polish-Soviet relations, 1943-1946 (Box 3)
    - Index (Folder 3: 1)
    - Nos. 1-125 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Nos. 126-215 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Nos. 216-399 (Folder 3: 4)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1941-1948
  - Boundaries
    - Germany (Folder 3: 5)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 3: 6)
  - Budget - Poland, 1940
    - General (Folder 3: 7)
    - Information and documentation projects (Folder 3: 8)
    - Ministries
      - Finance (Ministerstwo Skarbu) (Folder 3: 9)
      - Foreign Affairs (Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych) (Folder 3: 10)
      - Justice (Ministerstwo Sprawiedliwosci) (Folder 3: 11)
      - National Defense (Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych) (Folder 3: 12)
      - Social Welfare (Ministerstwo Opieki Spolecznej) (Folder 3: 13)
    - President (Prezydent) (Folder 3: 14)
    - Prime Minister (Prezes Rady Ministrow) (Folder 3: 15)
    - State Comptroller (Naczelna Izba Kontroli (Folder 3: 16)
    - State Council (Rada Narodowa) (Folder 3: 17)
    - State employees (Folder 3: 18)
  - Catholic Church
    - General, 1945-1946 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Diplomatic relations with the Communist government of Poland, 1945 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Central European Federation Club, 1946-1947 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Czechoslovakia - Social conditions, 1947 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Espionage - Soviet Union, 1947 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Forced labor - Soviet Union. Map of camps, 1947 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Germans
    - Poland, 1945 (Folder 3: 25)
    - United States, 1942 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Great Britain. Parliament - Debates on Poland, 1945 August (Folder 3: 27)
  - Health - Poland, 1945 (Folder 3: 28)
  - International relations. Article by Zenon Slomkowski, 1943 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Jews
    - Kielce pogrom, 1946 (Folder 3: 30)
    - Palestine (Folder 3: 31)
    - United States
      - 1942 (Folder 3: 32)
      - 1945 (Folder 3: 33)
      - 1946 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Liga Morska i Kolonialna. Agreement with Liberia, 1934 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Lithuanian Americans, 1942 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw. Clippings, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Paderewski, Ignacy
    - General, 1941 and 1947 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Guest book, 1941 January-1945 January. (Folder 4: 3)
      Contains signatures of prominent Poles visiting estate of Ignacy Paderewski
  - Poland
    - Economic conditions, 1942 (Folder 4: 4)
    - History - 1945-
      - General, 1945-1948 (Folder 4: 5)
      - Reconstruction, 1945-1948 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Politics and government
      - 1939 (Folder 4: 7)
      - 1945 (Folder 4: 8)
      - 1946 (Folder 4: 9)
      - 1947 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych (Ministry of Foreign Affairs)
    - List of Polish consular offices in 1946 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Resolutions after withdrawal of recognition, 1945 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Poland. Polskie Centrum Informacyjne (New York) (Folder 4: 13)
  - Polish American Congress., See also Refugees (Folder 4: 14)
  - Polish Americans
    - Awards and medals (Folder 4: 15)
    - Organizations, 1941-1942 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Raczkiewicz, Wladyslaw. Fliers (Folder 4: 17)
  - Recognition (International Law). Article by Jozef Kazimierz Gidynski, "Nonrecognition in Conflicts of Laws Situation," 1946? (Folder 4: 18)
    Typescript (deals with legal aspects of non-recognized governments)
  - Refugees - Poland
    - Germany, 1947
      - General (Folder 4: 19)
      - Polish-American Congress report illustrated with photographs (Folder 4: 20)
    - United States, Komitet dla Spraw Wysiedlencow Polskich, 1946 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Slomkowski, Zenon., See International relations
  - United State. Congress. Materials with references to Poland, 1947-1947 (Folder 4: 22)
  - World War, 1939-1945 (Box 5)
    - Armistice, Plans for (Folder 5: 1)
    - Atrocities (Folder 5: 2)
    - Civilian relief
      - General
        - 1940 (Folder 5: 3)
        - 1941
          - General (Folder 5: 4)
          - Press (Folder 5: 5)
        - 1942
          - General (Folder 5: 6)
          - Press (Folder 5: 7)
        - 1943 (Folder 5: 8)
      - Canada, 1941-1943 (Folder 5: 9)
      - Commission for Polish Relief, 1940-1942 (Folder 5: 10)
      - Internment camps, 1942 (Folder 5: 11)
      - Jews
        - General, 1941-1942 (Folder 5: 12)
        - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1942 (Folder 5: 13)
        - General Jewish Council, 1942 (Folder 5: 14)
        - World Jewish Congress, 1942 (Folder 5: 15)
      - Lend-lease operations (1941-1945), 1942 (Folder 5: 16)
      - Medical supplies, 1942 (Folder 5: 17)
      - Persia, 1942 (Folder 5: 18)
      - Poland. Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej (Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare)
        - New York Branch, 1942 (Folder 5: 19)
        - Znamiecki, Aleksander (Folder 5: 20)
      - Polish Americans
        - General, 1942 (Folder 5: 21)
        - Sumowski, Jerzy. Typescript, 1941. (Folder 5: 22)
          Includes comments on need to involve Polish Americans in war relief
      - Shipments (Folder 5: 23)
      - Soviet Union
        - General
          - General, 1941 (Folder 5: 24)
          - List of telegrams, n.d. (Folder 5: 25)
        - Expenses, 1941-1942 (Folder 5: 26)
        - Jews. Relief accorded to by the Polish authoroties, 1941-1943 (Folder 5: 27)
        - Poland. Ministerstwo Pracy i Opieki Spolecznej (Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare), 1942 (Folder 5: 28)
      - Strakaczowa, Aniela, 1943-1945 (Folder 5: 29)
      - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (Folder 5: 30)
      - War Chest, 1942 (Folder 5: 31)
  - Young Men's Christian Associations, 1941-1942 (Folder 5: 32)
- BULLETINS, 1946-1964 (Box 6)
  - General (Folder 6: 1)
  - Biuletyn Informacyjny
    - 1946
      - January-July (Folder 6: 2)
      - August-December (Folder 6: 3)
    - 1947 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Glos Wolny
    - 1948 (Folder 6: 5)
    - 1949 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Goniec Karpacki, 1944 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Informacja Placowek, 1945 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Intermarium
    - 1947 (Folder 6: 9)
    - 1948 (Folder 6: 10)
  - List Informacyjny (Adam Pragier)
    - 1945 (Folder 6: 11)
    - 1946 (Folder 6: 12)
    - 1947 (Folder 6: 13)
  - Polish News Bulletin of the American and British Embassies-Warsaw, 1964 March-April (Folder 6: 14)
  - Sprawy Polskie, 1947 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Zwiazki Ziem Wschodnich Rzeczpospolitej, 1948 (Folder 6: 16)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1942-1949 (Box 7)
  - General
    - General. Programs, 1942-1943 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Great Britain. Government brochures, 1946-1947 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Polish Armed Forces, 1940-1944 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Poland. Polskie Rzadowe Centrum Informacyjne (New York), (Polish Information Center, New York), 1941-1944 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Bialy Orzel: White Eagle, 1943 and 1945 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Polish Review, 1943 and 1945 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Sprawy Polskie
    - 1948 (Folder 7: 7)
    - 1949 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Sprawy Sowieckie, 1947 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Wiadomosci Krajowe, 1947
    - January-June (Folder 7: 10)
    - July-November (Folder 7: 11)